[Music]
look
i get it you've heard a thousand times
about how important it is to stay
hydrated and drink water etc etc
but you probably didn't realize that
being dehydrated by as little as two
percent
can actually reduce exercise capacity by
up to ten percent
you also may not know that some studies
have shown up to 30 percent of athletes
are actually over hydrated so giving you
basic concepts like
just drink a gallon of water a day or
eight cups or half your body weight in
ounces
i guess these are okay suggestions but
they're far from optimal
so how do you actually figure out how
much water you're supposed to drink so
that you're not under
or over hydrated well that's exactly
what i want to walk you through today
in this episode of 55 minute physiology
how to develop
individualized hydration plans so you
can maximize your physical performance
so a little bit of more what we're going
to cover more specifically
i'll talk about how much water you
actually need to drink and why different
diets mean you need to have different
amounts of actual water
how to test yourself and again i
individualize and personalize this
entire process for you and your clients
why it all matters how it all works
what's the physiology what's about
chemistry behind what's going on in your
body
what and how much you actually sweat so
help you figure out whether or not
you're a high
low or moderate sweater and are you a
high salt sweater or not
that all directly influences in what you
need to put back in
and or drink during your workouts i'll
cover sports drinks and electrolytes
and everything else that you need to
know to maximize your hydration
while we're here i've also got a special
present for you
i'm going to cover what i consider to be
five criminally
underrated mc's and i'm going to
sprinkle this in throughout the entire
presentation
to make sure you don't ever skip ahead
because you're not going to want to miss
this part
all right have i sold you enough on the
importance and how much fun we're going
to have
talking about hydration fantastic let's
get rolling now i don't have to really
convince you being dehydrated is bad for
performance
but you may have not realized that hyper
hydration is equally problematic
this is a great example that i love to
use from ufc fighter
and champion max holloway he actually
got pulled from one of his
world title fights just a couple of days
before because they were concerned that
he had
water poisoning it's very very common
for fighters to drink excessive amounts
of water in the days leading up to a
fight for
weight cutting and other purposes but
what you may not have realized is this
can actually have
significant physical problems and be
associated with it turns out this wasn't
actually the case he actually just had a
really bad concussion
but it does highlight the fact of what
can happen or potentially or
theoretically
with being over hydrated in fact if you
look at the literature
we see this happen fairly consistently
it's what we call exercise-induced
hyponatremia
so hypo being low neutrinos actually
means sodium
on the periodic table actually n a
stands for sodium so hyponatremia
means exercise induced reductions in
sodium concentration in the blood
that's almost always caused by excessive
drinking of
pure water so we don't want to also have
ourselves in a situation where we're
saying okay we want to be hydrated
because we know dehydration is bad
therefore we're just going to chug water
consistently this is very very
problematic
in the extremes people can actually die
right we again we see this happen in
marathons and ultra marathons and
triathlons
almost every single year it's been
associated with you know the accidental
killing of kids when
for punishment uh fraternity hazing and
many other things
now those are fairly extreme examples
it's not super common but it does happen
more realistically though is you're
probably hurting performance
by just chugging water so we don't want
to have that happen either
now i was a bit dramatic in the
introduction saying up to 30 percent of
athletes
that has been shown in fact if you look
across the breadth of the literature
it ranges anywhere between one to thirty
percent of athletes are hyper hydrated
during competition it depends on a lot
of factors
but it does highlight the fact that this
is a potential and it is something that
we want to get away from
the point of this video was to get as
close to optimization right now i hate
that word we're never going to get there
but i think we can get closer so rather
than just giving people blanket
statements
we want to avoid hypo hydration we want
to avoid hyper hydration let's
search for optimal so what's that look
like
well the standard things we tell people
like drink half your body weight in
ounces per day
it's extremely problematic here's why
if you were to follow this and you were
say 150-pound athlete that's mean you
drink 75 ounces
or about a half a gallon per day well
that has three major problems
problem number one nobody does it
if you look at the science anywhere
between 50 to 90
of people actually fail to hit that
number so why do we continue to tell
people to do something and we do it in a
fashion that they're not actually going
to achieve
and number two and three though that i'm
more concerned with is this number two
it doesn't actually account for
differences in exercise or physical
activity
right so we're telling people that are
300 pounds or 120 pounds
or people that live in florida or people
that live in washington state
people that are football players high
school lacrosse athletes
soccer players mma fighters perfect
we're telling all them to drink roughly
the same amount of water
i hope i don't have to convince you that
that is absurd again it's not
bad but it's far from optimal
okay and then thirdly it's not
personalized
i mean you simply know people who stand
and just start sweating
or others like my amazing wife natasha
i don't think she can sweat like it just
doesn't happen right
and so we need to develop a system that
says okay
how do we put you in a position so
you're not hyper or
hypo hydrated right so if you look at
two
athletes i've been very fortunate to
know uh steffy cohen right you have 121
pound girl who competes in powerlifting
scott holtzman he can be up to 190
pounds gonna cut down to 155 pounds
and fight in three five minute rounds
she's you know
25 years old and he's 35 years old
you really think they should be both
drinking half their body weight ounces
totally different sports
he lives in most time east tennessee she
lives in florida
different climates different humidity
just absurd right making it even
different let's take two different girls
here they both weigh about 120
ish 25 pounds lauren lives in texas
again steffy in florida different sports
there's just no way i can optimize both
of their performance on the same
fluid prescription okay
so let's really get into the specifics
about how to develop this individualized
hydration plan
well the solution to me is in three
parts
right part number one is you have to
start your exercise
in what we call a you hydrated state
from there
we want to prevent hypo hydration during
exercise
and then part three we want to fully
replenish the fluids we lost
from the exercise bout before we start
the next session right
now depending on whether or not we
actually start hypohydrate that
influences whether or not we can prevent
hydration
or hypohydration during the exercise
okay
in addition part number three then rolls
back into part number one so if you
don't fully replenish the fluids
an optimal hydrate post workout then
you're never gonna start you hydrated
for your next one
so although i've set these in up into
three different areas
it's really the same thing or like i
said differently they're all directly
going to influence
the other one another way to think about
how i break how i'm going to break up
this video is
what do you have to do during the day
what do you have to do during your
workout and what do you have to do
after your workout so let's go ahead and
jump into number one which is starting
you hydrated or that optimal state but
before we do that
let's jump into my special
criminally underrated mc number one now
these five are in random order
there's no particular preference and i'm
not claiming these are the only or most
underrated
mc's ever these are just five that jump
to my forefront as people
who don't get enough shine or love for
their just
incredible skills on the microphone
first and foremost one of my favorites
ever cool modi
if you're thinking yourself i've never
heard of this guy that's my point
this is the problem cool modi is
legendary he had
uh incredible battles with ll cool j
back in the early 90s or
probably even late 80s he's one of the
first innovators of fast rap
you know not many people i don't
actually he might be the very first ever
true fast rapper
one of the first ever to to put in
complex vocabulary as well
uh just an assassin on the microphone
really and for the most part he's the
one that
that hip-hop aficionados generally
credit as the guy that really invented
modern day battle rap so prior to him it
was sort of like
baby battle rap if you will but he's one
of the first that came out in the
microphone and just
flamed people he was one of the first
that actually went up people
like straight and went at them
personally and attacked them
like that in fact i would recommend
going and listening to
his verse on his diss song of elo cool j
and if you find the verse or the part
when he does his
famous l lines
it's unreal all right one of the best
verses in hip-hop history
period right have fun looking at it
all right back to the topic
so i introduced this a couple of slides
ago i didn't really talk about it though
but what we're really getting after is
a combination of what we call
homeostasis and hormesis
okay so homeostasis basically says we
want to come back to baseline and
hormesis says
there's a toxicity level for everything
and i've already explained that to you
being under hydrated being hyper
hydrated no
if we draw an analogy to say your low
back here
now most people know that when you're
say doing a deadlift or hinging that you
want your low back to be neutral
okay you want it to be in the middle
this is optimal you don't want it to be
hyper flexed
or hyper extended but if you had to pick
between one of them
being hyper extended is probably a
little safer than being hyper flexed
extremely high risk of injury lower risk
this
is perfect but that's better hydration
would be the same
okay if you had to pick one i would say
be hyper hydrated
drink a little bit more water than
necessary that's probably a whole lot
safer
a little bit of dehydration has
immediate drops in performance
you have to go pretty far into hyper
hydration before you start dropping
performance
and really far before you actually would
cause something like cardiac arrest or
hypothermia to the point of death
okay but the concept nonetheless that i
love to make sure
everyone understands and thinks about in
all aspects of nutrition and training
is that going from low to normal can be
very helpful in this particular case
oh you're hot you're hyper hydro or
you're you're dehydrated
let's give you some you went from low to
normal that's very helpful
and sometimes going from normal to a
little high
is even helpful sometimes not but almost
always go from high to extremely high
does the opposite right it hits that
toxicity curve and you start going down
in performance
and water is no different okay now this
concept is true for minerals
your ph blood pressure temperature
hormone concentrations
almost everything truly achieving
optimal performance in the body is
almost never a case of
more it's almost always a case of being
at the exact right concentration
you get the idea here right so how much
water do you actually need to drink well
it depends on several factors
this is a very nice classic study from a
decade or so ago and what they looked at
is different amounts of fluid
concentrations that you have to drink
based on your work
and i wouldn't expect anyone to memorize
this especially kids in my class i don't
care about these numbers i'm just
showing you the concept
of actually approaching hydration in a
thoughtful way which says i'm going to
account for your physical activity
right so let's assume you're at an
ambient temperature of 40 degrees
right here and if you're just resting
all day long you may only need to drink
say three liters of fluid a day which is
three quarters of a gallon
but as you go from resting to light work
to moderate work to heavy work
you might have to double the amount of
fluid oh you also start increasing
temperature well now what happens right
so really this is a more
specific way to approach hydration is to
factor in both your activity level as
well as hydration
now if they got real fancy they could
factor in
humidity but you get the point okay
again don't memorize these numbers just
think about how much it scales
at the low end 35 degrees which is not
that hot
and you're kind of resting maybe two
liters a day is fine at the high end
though
you might need to be at five times that
you're working your ass off and it's hot
you might have to again quintuple that
number okay
so like i said most people fail to hit
these nutritional guidelines of getting
half
your body weight in ounces for water and
so i think it's important for us to have
a little discussion about where the
actual fluids are coming from in your
body
depending on the study you look at
you're going to see numbers that look
something like this about half of the
fluid you get is actually from direct
water intake or it should be
the other 30 percent comes from fluids
so this is non
direct water fluids like tea coffee
etc and then about 20 from your food
and now this varies dramatically though
based on a whole bunch of factors but
these are fairly common numbers
for example you may not realize that the
vast majority of your food is actually
water
in fact if you look at some of these
fruits and vegetables most of them are
going to be 85 percent plus
water uh look at a cucumber right 96
water watermelons 90 plus percent
berries melons these are all 90
bananas start to get a little bit lower
but they're still like 80 plus percent
85 percent
water so if you're eating a diet
extremely high in fresh fruits and
vegetables
guess what you're also getting a lot of
water right as you'll see in a second if
you change your diet
you may have to start drinking more
specific or
going out of your way to drink more
water even things like eggs are still 75
and muscle is you know about 65
it's actually about say actually if you
go watch my hypertrophy video
you'll see these numbers in in muscle
but it's usually about 75
water muscle is when you take it out
though and cook it you course dehydrated
and so when you eat
actual meat it's about 65 but the point
is still being it's a very high water
content item bread
still also depending on the type of
stuff it can easily be 65
water the only place where this gets a
little bit tricky is one of my favorite
food items which is a biscuit
only about three percent water if you've
ever made a biscuit you're like oh
this makes total sense it's a very dense
very thick food item so it's very low
nonetheless point being let's compare
those to a different diet
one that looks more like that okay
now it doesn't take an extremely
intelligent person to think wait a
minute there's probably a whole lot less
water
in something that has been baked and
dehydrated
than there is a tomato or yogurt
or anything like that right so the
problem with these highly processed
foods
are they are both water sparse and
they're highly salted
this is generally what we mean when we
say processed right so you go from a
diet of
very high water rich very
low almost completely devoid of salt
then you switch to a diet that is
extreme that's basically the direct
opposite
and you wonder why we have different
hydration issues okay or i guess another
way to think about this is if you work
with an athlete who eats basically like
this
they're just simply going to have to go
out of their way to drink a lot more
water
if you switch to a diet more like that
you don't need to spend as much time
chugging your eight glasses water day
because you're getting so much more from
your food
and your salt intake is a lot lower now
i'll talk later in the video about salt
intake how much to do
and spoiler it's not bad for you so that
and of itself de facto is not the
problem the problem is just you combine
that with
also having low water intake in your
food
and so now we have hydration issues
in fact again if you look at some of the
research and this
really does depend on the country you're
looking at the studies are very
inconsistent here but
most people consume about 10 percent of
their salt
in their food okay about 15 is added at
the table so sprinkling some table on
your eggs when you
there's some salt on your eggs when you
sit at the table
and then the other 75 comes from food
processing
so again you can imagine an athlete or
someone like me who has
eats very little processed food that 75
goes down to like 10. so now my salt
intake has actually
dropped off almost entirely like right
it's hugely down
so depending on your athlete if they eat
extremely clean extremely poor some
combination you're gonna really need to
adjust their salt intake because what
you're gonna see later
you don't want them being too low of
salt either that has major implications
and major problems
so think about this let me go into it so
these individuals if you go back to this
original chart instead of having
20 their water coming 20 of their water
coming from the food they eat
they may be only at 10 right
again because of the low water content
of the food
so they may have to adjust they may need
to get to something more like three
quarters of their body weight in ounces
with a higher percentage of their water
coming or their fluids coming from water
intake
up to now 60 right so point being crappy
diet means you got to go out of your way
to drink a whole lot more water
if you eat real food most of the time
you don't have to sit around drinking as
much water
right so rather than relying on a stupid
generic number let's measure and see
all right so let me walk you through
exactly how you should measure your
hydration to figure out
whether or not you should be at this
half or three quarters or even higher
okay some different options for you in
general though you need to perform all
of these tests immediately upon waking
or pretty close to it
okay if you want to get really fancy and
precise you can buy
things like this these are what we'd use
in laboratory
in fact most of our studies this is
something that we measure the very first
thing as soon as
the individuals or the athletes come
into the lab right
urine specific gravity is what it's
called and there's all kinds of models
uh
these devices are not extremely
expensive i have several professional
athletes that do this every single day
right multiple times in fact we use this
one
the osmo check quite often with
professional athletes
yeah five six hundred bucks you know
anywhere actually between two hundred
and a thousand to get a reliable one
for you at home that maybe is a bit much
but for them if this is what you do for
a living
it's not excessive it's not crazy
you could also use something like this
this is another device that i've tested
and used in our laboratory like an in
body
so it's basically a scale that you stand
on and it will tell you your body weight
and body composition
and it also tells you your hydration
level is it perfect
no but it's reliable enough so that you
can use it
these things actually can also scale up
from a few hundred bucks to
extremely expensive so if you are
talking about in-home personal use i'll
show you
a different system but if you're a gym
owner
or you work with athletes consistently i
would strongly encourage you
invest in one of these machines in in
some form or fashion
right you can get a lot of information
from them
if you are the person who is at home
though and you're like hey bro the
reason i'm watching your free video
is because i can't afford two thousand
dollars for a scale that tells my
hydration
here's what you can do use a combination
of both the color of your urine
as well as the how thirsty are you
questionnaire
so basically every morning you wake up
you fill out say a scale of one to ten
how thirsty you are
you also you know do your morning
business here
and then you look at the color okay and
you can use this scale that i've
provided or any host or combination of
them
to measure that now one thing to keep in
mind uh you don't need to be peeing
crystal clear
you know that's not necessary for
hydration in fact you can see it right
there
but do remember that the toilet dilutes
so you want to pay attention to the
color of your stream if you
if you will rather than the color in the
doll because think about it
if you say pee out six ounces but you
pee it into a gallon of water
the gallon of the water which is clear
dilutes the color dramatically so you
look like you're more hydrated than you
actually are
so take into consideration the color of
the actual urine versus
the toilet i promise you every time we
have people do this and
they come in the lab they have to pee in
a little cup and they look at it like oh
my god it's yellow
and we measure it we're like no you're
hydrated i'm like what the hell because
you're used to seeing it diluted into a
gallon of water in the bottom of your
toilet
okay so you can start right there i'll
come back
we'll add this system as we go
but let's move on to step number two
then which is a bit more complicated
preventing your exercise induced hyper
hydration
but while we're here let's do un
criminally underrated mc number two
okay one of my favorites of all time
i think it's most hip-hop people
know cool maldi but a lot of people even
in our sphere don't give enough love to
dub c
willie calhoun is the name i think he
is one of the most original in terms of
his delivery
are his lyrics as tight and as flawless
as cool mondays probably not
but man there are a few people that hit
the notes have as much versatility in
his delivery
as dubsy he's been around for a long
time one of the founding members of the
world famous legendary west side
connection
a california classic swc
also probably the person who made
walk the dance
famous right so just legendary guy i
can't get enough of this dude
even on bad songs i'm like man he's just
so entertaining and flawless
on the mic so much love to you my friend
dub c
moving on okay
this is a really nice article if you're
loving this video and you're this far
along and you want more information i
recommend you going checking out this
practical hydrations for sport
by a whole bunch of authors a lot of
them have published
exceptional work in the area of sports
nutrition but they talk about something
and what i always preach
which is you want to know hydration
optimization the answer is it depends
and requires individualization
and they outline what that means and so
i'm not going to walk you through the
entire table today
but you can see there are a lot of
things that go into the risk factors
associated with being hypo or hyper
hydrated so
again i would recommend that you take a
look at this article they talk about
everything from clothing
environmental consideration availability
of fluids
water breaks the different water station
male female
body composition how long the exercise
sessions are
etc etc etc so it's a really nice
in-depth article
i'm going to summarize it for you in the
next five minutes though
you'll get more out of just reading it i
promise but if we look at sports like
you're seeing in this particular image
you realize that
these are fairly low risk of being hype
hyper hypohydrated why
why do basketball players wrestlers
football players volleyball players
track and field gymnasts
gymnasts and hockey would you see the
new logo this is the seattle kraken
our new hockey team what a badass logo
huh and what an
awesome name point being why are all of
these sports
not at an extremely high risk of hypo
hydration or dehydration during the
sport
think about well most of them are either
not extremely long in duration
or they allow because of the rules of
the game the athletes to take a break
every few minutes and drink water
right so basketball player every five or
six minutes is going to go get in a
break and sit on the bench
football player you're coming off after
every drive you have plenty of times to
drink water
all the other sports have hockey you're
in shifts right
gymnastics you do your routine then you
go sit down
right so these sports you of course want
to drink water but you're not at
extremely high risk of becoming
dehydrated because at least you have
those bricks when we compare that to
things like soccer
right you don't get a substitute in
soccer i mean occasionally one person
will get subbed out but you're playing a
45 minute half
then you get a break and then you do
another 45 minute half there's no time
for water
rugby is the same thing right same
similar with combat sports like boxing
right yeah okay we have a little bit of
a break in between rounds but michael i
got gloves on my hands right i got a
face mask on if i'm in practice i got
mouthpiece in
and i'm breathing so hard i have such
limited window it's very difficult to
maintain your hydration over that hard
of work
for 36 minutes right and this becomes a
real problem
when we look at and extend this out to
endurance events that are lasting more
than two hours so
any cycling swimming running obstacle
races things like that that are
two hours or longer are going to have a
problem
now the amount each individual athlete
sweats
can differ pretty wildly the typical
rates we say are between one to five
pounds per hour but it depends on a lot
of factors like their body size
the exercise intensity and duration how
hydrated or dehydrated they were prior
to the workout
the heat and humidity all of these
things factor into it
i will tell you in my personal
experience in the combat sports
five pounds in an hour is not uncommon
i've seen plenty people go past this in
fact i've seen
it it's really common for them to drop
four pounds in an hour and they're not
even working that hard they don't even
feel it right they're just like oh yeah
their entire have you ever seen people
in jiu jitsu or kickboxing or wrestling
i mean they're just a pit of walking
sweat right everything is soaked to the
bone
and they walk out and those are under
fairly normal circumstances
you can see mike lee here on the ground
20 in one professional box who just
fought for a world title
he's a sweat machine right it takes him
nothing and he's just covered and sweat
up and down
so this five pounds per hour i think is
a very
um it's not extreme to get up that high
i actually i think one to two pounds per
hour is
is pretty low uh for the sports i work
in um i would
generally not see that even for a very
small girl they're going to do way more
than
a pound an hour okay so things to
consider with it then you know the sweat
rate you know you're kicking out three
four five pounds per hour
right and if you look at this chart here
you can see the different sports so
marathon running soccer basketball
rowing etc
and they show you the different
temperature and the research shows us
how much sweat they're actually losing
somewhere in the neighborhood of about a
thousand
milliliters per hour which remember a
thousand milliliters is also
one liter okay one liter 2.2 pounds
so in this example right here this would
be
similar to saying 2.2 pounds per hour
okay
so you can scale up and down this would
of course be four and a half pounds or
so per hour
when it's 86 degrees out uh you can see
the ambient temperature again plays a
lot so
rowing in a 50 degree weather versus 85
and you almost doubled the spot right
but what's really interesting about this
chart is the next column
and that is how much are the how much
fluid are the athletes actually drinking
so if you're sitting there like we
talked about in soccer and you've lost
2.2 pounds how much did you actually
drink back
well a whole lot less why because you
only had half time to do it
marathon running even basketball
basketball does a lot better job right
but you're still under hydrating all
these other sports again very limited
access to water
so you're going to clearly significantly
under in fact the number we typically
use is about 50
most athletes will only drink back about
50 of the fluids they lose
which is obviously sub-optimal it's not
good for maintaining perfect performance
in-game competition but it also sets you
up to be hypo hydrated or dehydrated
post-workout meaning you have to drink
even more water to get just back to
baseline
so knowing that one thing we have to pay
attention to is thirst okay
we know thirst is an okay judge of
hydration
when you're sitting around doing nothing
that's why i actually recommended
maybe charting that or noting it first
thing in the morning however
it's a very poor indicator of hydration
needs during exercise
for a whole bunch of physiological
reasons we also know that people
under drink significantly during
exercise because you get tricked
especially in the cold so people will
under drink
during exercise unless you're prompted
how do you do that well you do things
like making sure that the water and
fluid is in their vision of sight
athletes and we know this from the
research are more likely to go grab more
water if they see it directly
so in practice in workouts rather than
having the water station around the
corner make sure it's right there in
front of them
there's a bunch of other ways you can
trick them okay
what we don't want to do is leave it up
the only athlete so as you can see this
professional athlete here
not making her best hydration choice all
right eating snow is probably not the
best way we can
for return hydration after a long hike
in the cold
all right so other factors that
influence
voluntary water intake the temperature
and i'm talking of the fluids right so
cold water athletes are more likely to
drink it
uh the flavor the amount of salt as well
as the visibility
so you want to make sure that you're
giving them things that are at the
appropriate temperature
they taste good they like them they have
some salt in them and you can see them
consistently
so this is why i think like again
setting out a water trough
is probably not the best thing you can
do you may want to give them something
that appeals to them a little bit more
right so you may be thinking yourself
this point all right i get it but again
does under hydrating really matter that
much
well let's talk about that we know that
about sixty percent of your body is
water and the other forty percent is
solid
right so it's a big chunk of what you
are but this can range from anywhere
between like fifty to seventy percent so
i have tested some athletes who
had an optimal hydration status they are
actually about fifty percent fluids and
others that are up to 70 percent
so it can range quite a bit and we know
water has critically important functions
physiologically
it's a transport medium right it's what
we use to get say carbohydrates through
our blood
and to get carbon dioxide out right it
moves things along
it's a lubricant for our joints it's
also a chemical reaction facilitator
so a lot of the biochemistry that you
learn in your exercise physiology class
of krebs cycle and beta oxidation
and all that stuff and hydrolysis of atp
right
in order to burn an atp together to get
that energy released that actually takes
water it's why it's called hydrolysis
so all the chemical or many of the
chemical reactions that have to go down
in your body for you to perform
require water it's a solvent which
allows you to do to dissolve
things in it and it also performs it
functions as basic structure
in a lot of cases more importantly
though in this particular context is
it's a thermal regulator and in fact the
reason you sweat
is so that you can get fluid on your
skin
once you then burn off that fluid that
releases energy that cools you down so
that's the actual reason why you sweat
you may have thought to yourself like i
know i sweat when i get hot but why
it's so that you can burn the fluid on
your skin
and then cool yourself down that way
okay so if we look at percent hydration
what that actually looks like
we typically talk about dehydration in
terms of percent of body weight loss
so if you're a hundred pounds and you've
lost one pound you are one percent
dehydrated
okay so we're always thinking about this
in context of percent of body weight
loss
i'll pretty much refer to it as percent
dehydration but that's what i'm
specifically referring to
we can see that if you're getting down
to as lo as early as one to two percent
you start to kind of get thirsty
but you start to hit four percent
reductions in body weight and we can see
up to 20 to 30
reductions in physical work capacity so
by losing as little as four percent of
your body weight in water
i mean you're you're not even close to
the podium you're dead last you're
getting smashed right you're not even
making it to the fourth quarter
you can imagine then what happens at as
little as two percent you start a strong
thirst
vague discomfort and you're already down
right so we don't have incredibly strong
signals for hydration
even though we're losing performance so
we have to rely on things besides just
oh drink water when you're thirsty
okay now you can see the numbers here
six seven percent
um i've seen folks get a lot higher than
that you can see in the examples
of what we do with weight cut stuff for
combat sports which i don't like i don't
advise i hate it i'm not for it
it's just something i have to deal with
okay so i'm not advocating doing this
it's just a process we have to deal with
my point being you're not prob
you're not going to collapse at seven
percent but you're going to feel you're
going to feel terrible
okay you're some people may i guess but
um
those are not uncommon numbers for us to
get to i guess is is
the point okay but more specifically
what happens to performance
you can start to draw a line here
horizontally we're talking percent body
weight loss and vertically exercise
capacity
we know that again you start hitting
this like two to two and a half percent
and we start to see upwards of ten
percent or more reductions in
performance
you start getting out here three percent
four percent five percent
and now you're down to you've lost
thirty percent
right like you're toast you can't
perform like that at all
why that happens well
we we see that you you have everything
from a reduction of blood volume which
is
in one of my endurance videos i talk
about probably the most significant
predictor of exercise performance
endurance performance is blood volume
while you lose that you start dipping
down a core temperature goes up you
start to over rely on muscle glycogen
which is great for early energy but once
that's burned out
you fatigue very quickly you can't
dissipate the heat so you get
and you maintain your core temperature
or exceed it which is a problem
and you even start to reduce the ability
to direct
sweat to the blood or to the skin to
their participated so it becomes a real
problem
so to give you some context of the
numbers here imagine you're a 185 pound
athlete
a one percent drop would actually be
about two pounds of fluid loss
again this is very normal two percent
drop would be 3.7 pounds so imagine
yourself being 185 pounds
you've done a workout you weighed
yourself pre and post and now you've
lost four pounds
that won't feel that bad but you've
already dropped your physical abilities
by two to two and a half percent
depending right three percent would be
again in that normal range
five pounds in an hour is not that crazy
and you're already down to
you know 85 ability maybe
so we really got to pay attention to
this stuff the other thing that being a
slightly dehydrated does
past just reducing your ability to
perform is it increases your perception
of difficulty
so athletes that are dehydrated feel
like the workout is harder
so even if you're say doing a workout at
guaranteed 80
of your work capacity or something it's
going to just feel more difficult than
it should
nobody wants that right you're not going
to feel great you're not going to
perform better
right probably again because you're
increasing your rate of muscle glycogen
use
so you're we know a byproduct of
anaerobic metabolism is
acid buildup and waste and so you're
going to feel that
whether you're not your performance has
gone down you're going to feel
or it's going to feel more difficult
so if we talk about other sports like
baseball in this example
so your in-game hydration so much how
much fluid you have to drink during
exercise
is probably less critical for those
sports because again if you take
you know trevor bauer here if he's
pitching indoors and it's 65 degrees in
that stadium
the intensity of the workout's not very
high it's long but there's a lot of
breaks he has plenty of time to drink
water
and it's not hot he's very unlikely to
have to maximize his hydration during
the game now we still do it with him
right because we want to maximize your
performance but you're not going to see
huge problems with sports that cause
less than two percent of body weight
loss
right in other words i think that's
worded off by there but you get right
if they don't cause more than two
percent body weight inhaling hydration
is a little bit less
having said that though some studies
have
shown that progressing from one to four
percent dehydration
continually deteriorates things like
timing and accuracy
so in this particular study they looked
at basketball players
and saw that they experienced
progressive deteriorations
in performance and accuracy as
dehydration progressed from one to four
percent
so like i said you may not lose your
maximal
endurance abilities in your baseball
game but if your timing and accuracy is
off your spin rate goes down
all of a sudden that fly by the left
field hits the stands and
that's a big difference right so we want
to make sure that we're paying attention
to that again if you want to optimize
you might as well just optimize don't
just do the bare minimum
so how much water do i have to actually
drink during my game or my workout
well the answer is number three
on our underrated mc list now this is an
individual
if you've never heard of cool mode okay
if you've never heard of
dub c all right i almost guarantee if
you're not a mega hip-hop herd you've
never heard of this gentleman
and it breaks my heart i still don't
understand this
and this is my friend chino xl and i say
friend loosely i have no idea who he is
i've never met him
but he is a complete savage
go google chino excel wake up show and
thank me later
okay he is unreal just
one of the top ever embassies with
things like word play
metaphor one of the originators of
punchline rap just
destructive in that ability um hit like
i said his swaying
swain tech freestyles are just
incredible
for whatever reason man he just never
kind of landed with
albums they just they never did when he
never kind of made it up out of this
even though he's been rapping and
putting out just tremendous stuff for 20
years
i think he has a new album coming out
soon hopefully and so
i'm excited about that but i mean geez
you catch this guy on a
feature track of somebody else's song or
any of the stuff he's done
it's just next level lyrically and
that's what i appreciate about hip hop
most
so go check out yourself some chino xl
okay back to business all right this is
what happens
when you drink fluids properly during
your workouts or not what you're seeing
here is a chart and they've plotted
exercise time so imagine
they put you on a treadmill they say run
as long as you possibly can until you
can go no longer
so when the individuals did this they
averaged about 77
minutes right so that's how long they
could run in this treadmill when they
weren't allowed to drink water
when they gave them some that 77 minutes
turned into
103 minutes right so you saw like what
at least a 25 minute increase in your
ability to run
at the same exact speed by drinking two
milliliters per kilogram of body weight
every 15 minutes
of just water i hopefully this is
convincing you how important it is to
maintain hydration if you want to
maximize performance
now the example the example would be
here again if you take 185 pound
football player
they would be then 84 kilos you times
that by two that would be 168
milliliters
or around 5.6 ounces every 15 minutes
okay now i'm gonna make this system a
little bit simpler for you
if you can calculate these things great
this is the two millimeters per kilogram
of bodyweight every 15 minutes is the
number we use
but think about it this way if you go
buy a bottle of water from the store you
usually buy them in either 16 or 20
ounce bottles
so if you think okay a 20 ounce bottle
is this big and i know for 185 pound
person they have to drink like five or
six
which means i'm gonna drink you know
like a third or a quarter
of that water bottle every 15 minutes
plus or minus right this is probably
enough to get you in the ideal spot in
terms of just fluid intake
okay while we're here though i think
this is a good time to think about some
scientific units right so please
remember that a thousand milliliters is
one liter one pound is 16 ounces and one
liter is one kilo
right this will help you i promise
become better at your hydration and your
nutrition if you figure out units
science works in
si units america we work in the worst
system of units ever now i'll be honest
with you i don't always have all these
conversions memorized either
and so i just want to show you sort of
how i do this mental
mathematics and i'm never worried about
being super accurate i just want to help
you be able to get to a ballpark fairly
quickly
okay so if we know that a thousand
milliliters is one liter and one liter
is 2.2 pounds therefore
500 milliliters half that is about one
pound you follow me
if that's true half that 250 milliliters
is about a quarter of a pound
okay so one liter is one kilo 2.2 pounds
so 250 milliliters is about a quarter of
2.2 pounds
you get me there so a quarter of that
2.2 is half pounds
i know 16 ounces is 1 pound so if i know
half a pound is then about 8 ounces and
that's all i do okay
so if i know all that in mind and i and
i told somebody to drink eight ounces
when really their optimal number was 6.3
that's pretty damn close and it's about
as close as you're ever really going to
get
okay now i i'm in class
i make my students do this when we have
live classes but
if we're doing this one online you get
lucky okay
did i confuse you that wasn't the
simplest thing you've ever heard
all right fine i'll make it even easier
this is what i call the cheating method
if you want to figure out how much water
to drink
during your workouts take your body
weight in pounds
divide it by 30. right so that 185 pound
football player divided by 30 would be
about 6
which is pretty close to that 5.6 we
calculated
just a second ago have them drink that
every 15 minutes or so
and bada bing you're pretty close
all right come on
come on you have to love me for that
right i made that up all on my own just
for you i was sitting here thinking
they're going to whine that this is too
complicated they're never going to
i made the system easy for you you're
welcome you're welcome
okay now one of the challenges that we
do have to pay attention to with
hydration during exercise
is what we call gastric emptying so this
is your ability to get
water out of your tummy and into your
actual vessels
and anyone who's ever chugged way too
much water too fast and they go to do
their
workout or whatever and you literally
they no good right so one of the things
we know is difficult is at exercise
intensities of greater than 70 percent
gastric entering becomes really really
difficult and so you may have to
over hydrate a little bit prior to the
workout knowing it's going to be
difficult to get it in
during this is what we face almost every
time in mma or any of our combat sports
right
having said that it's very clear at this
point and i've seen it personally as
well
that this is trainable so if you just
work on drinking a little bit more fluid
the stomach will get better at this
and it won't be as difficult as you try
the one thing i will recommend though or
i won't recommend i will demand of you
is please don't try a hydration system
for the first time
ever in your race okay i've seen this
countless times make sure you practice
things
in practice before you go and do it in a
game
try it out try different amounts you
don't want to be in a world title fight
and someone feels like there's water
slashing around their belly it's going
to be awful
okay so practice what you preach try it
before games
this is also like i said why
pre-hydration is so beneficial okay
you may solve a lot of your problems
right so at this point i hope you're
fairly comfortable with how much fluid
to drink
but we haven't yet covered what you
should drink
but we're not going to do that here i
know your attention span is short and
we've been working really hard
so we're going to tackle that in part
two i'll see you in there